<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5213 SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dmm-fpc-cpdp SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dmm-fpc-cpdp.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dmm-srv6-mobile-uplane-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="SRv6-mobile-uplane">Segment Routing IPv6 for Mobile User Plane</title>

     <author fullname="Satoru Matsushima" initials="S." surname="Matsushima">
      <organization abbrev="SoftBank">SoftBank</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Tokyo</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <email>satoru.matsushima@g.softbank.co.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C." surname="Filsfils">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems, Inc.">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cf@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Miya Kohno" initials="M." surname="Kohno">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems, Inc.">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mkohno@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Pablo Camarillo" initials="P." surname="Camarillo">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems, Inc.">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pcamaril@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Daniel Voyer" initials="D." surname="Voyer">
      <organization abbrev="Bell Canada">Bell Canada</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniel.voyer@bell.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Charles E. Perkins" initials="C.E." surname="Perkins">
       <organization abbrev="Futurewei">Futurewei Inc. </organization>
       <address>
         <postal>
           <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
           <city>Santa Clara</city>
           <code>95050</code>
           <region>CA</region>
           <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+1-408-330-4586</phone>
         <email>charliep@computer.org</email>
       </address>
    </author>


    <date year="2018" />

    <workgroup>DMM Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>This document discusses the applicability of SRv6 (Segment Routing
      IPv6) to user-plane of mobile networks. The source routing capability 
      and the network programming nature of SRv6 will accomplish the mobile
      user-plane functions quite straightforwardly. The statelessness and 
      the ability to control underlying layer will be even more beneficial 
      to the mobile user-plane, in terms of providing flexibility and SLA 
      control for various applications. It also simplifies the network 
      architecture by eliminating the necessity of tunnels, such as GTP, 
      Mac-in-Mac, MPLS, and so on. In addition, Segment Routing can provide 
      an enhanced method for network slicing, which will also be briefly touched 
      by this document.  </t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

        <t>In mobile networks, mobility management systems provide
        connectivity while mobile nodes move around. While the
        control-plane of the system signals movements of a mobile node,
        user-plane establishes tunnel between the mobile node and anchor
        node over IP based backhaul and core networks. </t>

        <t>This document discusses the applicability of SRv6 (Segment
        Routing IPv6) to those mobile networks. SRv6 provides source
        routing to networks where operators can explicitly indicate a route
        for the packets from and to the mobile node. SRv6 endpoint nodes
        perform the roles of anchor of mobile user-plane. </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Conventions and Terminology">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
        
        <t>All segment routing and SRv6 network programming terms are
        defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/> and
        <xref target="I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming"/>.</t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="motivations" title="Motivations">
    
        <t>Current and future applications require a highly optimized
        data-path between mobile nodes and the entities of those
        applications in terms of latency, bandwidth, etc.,. However the
        current architecture of mobile management is agnostic about
        underlying topologies of transport layer. It rigidly fragments the
        user-plane into radio access, core and service networks and connects
        them by tunneling techniques through the user-plane roles such
        as access and anchor nodes. Such agnosticism and rigidness make it
        difficult for the operator to optimize the data-path.</t>
    
        <t>While the mobile network industry has been trying to solve that problems,
        applications are shifting to use IPv6 data-path, and network operators
        adopt IPv6 as their IP transport as well. SRv6 integrates both
        application data-path and underlying transport layer in data-path
        optimizations that do not require any other techniques.</t>
        
        <t>SRv6 source routing capability with programmable functions <xref
        target="I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming"/> can
        fulfill the user-plane functions of mobility management.  SRv6 takes
        advantage of underlying layer awareness and flexibility to deploy
        user-plane functions. Those are the motivations to adopt SRv6 for
        mobile user-plane.</t>

    
    </section>


    <section anchor="scenarios" title="Reference Architecture and Deployment Scenarios">
 
        <t>This section describes a referene architecture and possile deployment
        scenarios.</t>
        
        <t><xref target="fig_ref-arch"/> shows a reference architecture, based
        on 5G packet core architecture  <xref target="TS.23501"/>.
?
        
        <list style='symbols'>
        <t> UE  : User Equipment </t>
        <t> gNB : gNodeB </t>
        <t> UPF : User Plane Function </t>
        <t> SMF : Session Management Function </t>
        <t> AMF : Access and Mobility Management Function </t>
        <t> DN  : Data Network e.g. operator services, Internet access </t>
         </list>

	   </t>
        <t>
            <figure anchor="fig_ref-arch" title="Reference Architecture">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

                       
                                  +-----+                              
                                  | AMF |                                                                                    
                                  +-----+  
                                /    | [N11]  
                         [N2]  /  +-----+                              
                       +------/   | SMF |                                                                                    
                      /           +-----+                                          
                     /              / \  
                    /              /   \  [N4]
                   /              /     \                    ________
                  /              /       \                  /        \
  +--+      +-----+ [N3] +------+  [N9]  +------+  [N6]    /          \                   
  |UE|------| gNB |------| UPF1 |--------| UPF2 |--------- \    DN    /                                                                             
  +--+      +-----+      +------+        +------+           \________/


              ]]></artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure>
        </t>
        
        <t>A session from an UE gets assigned to an UPF. Sometimes more than 
        one UPF can be used for providing a certain kind of richer service 
        functions. UE gets its IP address from the DHCP block of its UPF. 
        The UPF advertises the IP address block towards the Internet ensuring 
        that return traffic is routed to the right UPF. </t>

        <t>The deployment of SRv6 to the mobile dataplane will happen in phases,
        so this document assumes the following two scenarios. </t>

         <section anchor="scenario1" title="Scenario1 : SRv6 on N3 and N9">

            <t>In this scenario, it is assumed that both gNB and UPF are SRv6
            nodes, thus SRv6 can be supported both on N3 and N9.</t>

            <t><xref target="fig_scenario1"/> shows scenario1. </t>

        <t>
            <figure anchor="fig_scenario1" title="Scenario 1">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
            
                                                             ________
                    SRv6           SRv6                     /        \
  +--+      +-----+ [N3] +------+  [N9]  +------+  [N6]    /          \                   
  |UE|------| gNB |------| UPF1 |--------| UPF2 |--------- \    DN    /                                                                             
  +--+      +-----+      +------+        +------+           \________/
           SRv6 node     SRv6 node       SRv6 node

              ]]></artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure>
        </t>
                    
        </section>

        <section anchor="scenario2" title="Scenario2 : IPv4 GTP on N3 and SRv6 on N9">

            <t>In this scenario, it is assumed that gNB does not support
            SRv6. It just supports GTP encapsulation based on IPv4. Hence, 
            SRv6 node interfacing with gNB should provide an interworking 
            function (IWF) between GTP and SRv6.</t>

            <t><xref target="fig_scenario2"/> shows scenario2, IPv4 GTP on N3 and SRv6 on N9. </t>

        <t>
            <figure anchor="fig_scenario2" title="Scenario 2">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
            
                                                             ________
                  IPv4 GTP         SRv6                     /        \
  +--+      +-----+ [N3] +------+  [N9]  +------+  [N6]    /          \                   
  |UE|------| gNB |------| UPF1 |--------| UPF2 |--------- \    DN    /                                                                             
  +--+      +-----+      +------+        +------+           \________/
                         SRv6 node       SRv6 node
                          (IWF)

              ]]></artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure>
        </t>
                    
        </section>

<!--
        <t>Details about SRv6 node representing user-plane functions
        are described in <xref target="uplane-functions"/>. </t>
-->

    </section>

    <section anchor="uplane-functions" title="Dataplane behaviors">
        
        <t>This section describes the mobile dataplane behaviors using SRv6.
        The terminology for the functions enabled on the SRv6 node refers to 
        <xref target="I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming"/>. </t>
        
        <t>There are two conceivable options in terms of the SRv6 SID allocation.
        One is "Traditional mode", which inherits the traditional mobile data 
        plane, and another one is "Enhanced mode", which aggregates the mobile 
        sessions and allocates SID per policy basis. </t>

      
        <section anchor="traditional_mode" title="Traditional Mode">
            
         <t> In the traditional mode, we assume that mobile user-plane
         functions are just as same as existing ones except the use of SRv6
         as the data plane instead of GTP-U. No impact to the rest part of 
         mobile system should be expected.</t>

         <t> In the traditional mobile network, an UE session is mapped 1-for-1 
         with a specific GTP tunnel (TEID). This 1-for-1 mapping is replicated 
         here as the sole pupose to replace the GTP encaps with the SRv6 encaps, 
         while not changing anything else. </t>
         
         <t> This mode is not likely to be considered for deploymet from the 
         scalability point of view. But this model minimizes the changed required
         to the entire system and it is a good startpoint for forming the common 
         basis. </t>

       
         <section anchor="packet_s1t" title="Packet flow for Scenario1">
         
               <t> Refer to <xref target="fig_scenario1"/>. 
			<list style="hanging">
               <t> UE_out  : (A,Z) </t>
               <t> gNB_out : (gNB, U1::1) -> T.Encaps.Reduced [U1::1] </t>
               <t> UPF1_out: (gNB, U2::1) -> END.MAP </t>
               <t> UPF2_out: (A,Z) -> END.DT </t>
               </list>

               The UE packet arrives to the gNB. The gNB performs a 
               T.Encaps.Reduced operations. Since there is only one SID, 
               there is no need to push an SRH. gNB only puts an outer IPv6 
               header with IPv6 DA U1::1. U1::1 represents an anchoring SID
               specific for that session at UPF1. The SID U1::1 is retrived
               retrieved through a control plane.</t>


               <t> Upon pacekt arrival on UPF1, the SID U1::1 is a local 
               End.MAP SID. This function maps the SID with the next anchoring
               point and replaces the SID by U2::1, that belongs to the next 
               anchoring point. </t>
               
               <t> Upon packe arrival on UPF2, the SID U2::1 corresponds to an 
               END.DT SID. It decapsulate the packet, peforms a lookup
               in a specific table and forward the packet towards the data
               network. </t>
               
               <t> For the reverse path, the same functions apply. </t>
               
               <t> For IPv6 user-traffic, a service provider can choose to 
               do SRH insertion, instead of doing SRH encasulation, so that 
               it would lower the overhead. In such case, the functions used 
               are T.Insert, END.MAP and END.T. </t>
        </section>
        
        </section>
        

        <section anchor="enhanced_mode" title="Enhanced Mode">
            
         <t>This mode improves the scalability. In addition, it provides key 
         improvements in terms of traffic steering and service chaining, 
         thanks to the use of an SR policy of multiple SIDs, instead of single 
         one in the Traditional mode. 
         
         <list style='symbols'>
          <t> Several UE share the same SR Policy (and composing SID) </t>
          <t> The SR policy MAY include SIDs for traffic steering and service chaining on top of the UPF anchor. </t>
          <t> The initiating SR node resovle the IP address into a SID list through a mechanism like reverse DNS, LISP, etc. </t>
          </list>

          </t>
                 
         <section anchor="packet_s1e" title="Packet flow for Scenario1">
               
               <t>  Refer to <xref target="fig_scenario1"/>. </t>
               <t> [Uplink]
               <list style="hanging">
               <t> UE_out  : (A,Z) </t>
               <t> gNB_out : (gNB, S1) (gNB, S1; SL=2) (A,Z) -> T.Encaps.Reduced [S1, C1, U2::1] </t> 
               <t> S1_out  : (gNB, C1) (U2::1, S1; SL=1) (A,Z) </t>
               <t> C1_out  : (gNB, U2::1) (A,Z) -> PSP </t>
               <t> UPF2_out: (A,Z) -> END.DT </t>
               </list>

               UE sends its packet (A,Z) on a specific bearer session to its 
               gNB. gNB's CP associates the session from the UE (A) with IPv6 
               address B and GTP TEID T. gNB's CP does a lookup on B (by reverseDNS, 
               LISP, etc.) to find the related SID list [S1, C1, U2::1]. 
              </t>



               <t> [Downlink]
               <list style="hanging">
               <t> [UPF2_in : (Z,A) -> UPF2 maps A with SID list [C1, S1, gNB] </t>
               <t> [UPF2_out: (U2::1, C1) (gNB, S1; SL=2) (Z,A) -> T.Encaps.Reduced </t>
               <t> [C1_out  : (U2::1, S1) (gNB, S1; SL=1) (Z,A) </t>
               <t> [S1_out  : (U2::1, gNB) (Z,A) -> PSP </t>
               <t> [gNB_out : (Z,A) </t>
               </list>
               </t>

                <t> As a generic property of Segment Routing, the SIDs 
                instantiated at UPF1 and UPf2 (U1::1 and U2::2) are shared 
                among several UE sessions. This menas that for 1 million UEs, 
                there will M T.Encaps operations and N U2::1 SIDS, where M 
                and N scales in the likely tens or low-hundreds.
               </t>

               <t> For IPv6 user-traffic, a service provider can choose to 
               do SRH insertion, instead of doing SRH encasulation, so that 
               it would lower the overhead. In such case, the functions used 
               are T.Insert, END.MAP and END.T. </t>

         </section>
  
         <section anchor="packet_s2e" title="Packet flow for Scenario2">
              
               <t>  Refer to <xref target="fig_scenario2"/>. 
               <list style='symbols'>
               <t> In Scenario2, gNB is unchanged and encapsulates packets into GTP. </t>
               <t> Interwork Function (IFW) removes GTP, finds SID list related to DA, add SRH with SID list. </t>
               <t> The SR policy MAY include SIDs for traffic steering and service chaining on top of the UPF anchor, in commono with Scenario1. </t>
               </list>
               </t>
               
               <t> 
               UE gets an IP address (A) from its L3 anchor point (U2::1)
               UE sends its packet (A,Z) on a specific bearer session to its gNB.
               gNB's CP associates the session from the UE (A) with IPv6 address B
               and GTP TEID T. </t>
         
               <t>[Uplink]
               <list style='hanging'>
               <t> gNB_out : (gNB, B) (GTP: TEID T) (A,Z) -> Interface N3 unchanged </t> 
               <t> IWF_out : (IWF, S1) (U2::1, S1; SL=1) (A,Z)  -> New END.GTP.UP </t>
               <t> S1_out  : (IWF, C1) (U2::1, C1; SL=1) (A,Z) </t>
               <t> C1_out  : (gNB, U2::1) (A,Z) -> PSP </t>
               <t> UPF2_out: (A,Z) -> END.DT </t>
               </list>
               </t>

               <t>[Downlink]
               <list style='hanging'>
               <t> UPF2_in : (Z,A) -> UPF2 maps A with SID list [C1, S1, IWF::TEID, gNB] </t>
               <t> UPF2_out: (U2::1, C1) (gNB, IWF::TEID, S1; SL=3) (Z,A) -> T.Encaps.Reduced </t>
         		<t> C1_out  : (U2::1, S1) (gNB, S1; SL=2) (Z,A) </t>
         		<t> S1_out  : (U2::1, IWF::TEID) (gNB, IWF::TEID, S1, SL=1) (Z,A) </t>
         		<t> gNB_out : (Z,A) </t>
         		</list>
         		</t>

         		<t> For the downlink traffic, the IWF is stateless. All the state is 
         		in the SRH imposed by the UPF. The UPF must have this UE-Base state 
         		anyway since it's the anchor point. </t>

         		<t> For the uplink traffic, the state at the IWF is shared, not 
         		dedicated on a per UE/session basis. Hence, the states likely scale 
         		in the low 10/100s and this is more scalable compared to the millions 
         		of sessions.</t>

               <t> For IPv6 user-traffic, a service provider can choose to 
               do SRH insertion, instead of doing SRH encasulation, so that 
               it would lower the overhead. In such case, the functions used 
               are T.Insert, END.MAP and END.T. </t>
         </section>

         </section>
   
    </section>
        

    <section anchor="netslice" title="Network Slicing Considerations">

        <t>A mobile network may be required to implement "network slices",
        which logically separate network resources. User-plane functions 
        represented as SRv6 segments would be part of a slice.</t>
        
        <t>A simple way to represent slice would be to apply L2/L3vpn 
        described in <xref
        target="I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming"/> . Segment
        Routing with [IGP flex algo] would provide even more advanced
        separation based on metrics like link-delay Thus, a service
        provider would be able to have network slices per required SLA. </t>
        
        <t>The SRv6 SID and quite a few SR extended capability would be 
        a powerful tool for providing logical separation/integration 
        within a network. Details are for further study. </t>

    </section>

        <section anchor="c-plane" title="Control Plane Considerations">

        <t>This documents focuse on the dataplane behavior. The control planes
        could be based on the existing 3GPP based signaling, LISP/ILSR, DNS/reverse 
        DNS lookup, MFA, etc., and to be discussed further. </t>

        <t>It's notable that SRv6's network programming nature allows a 
        flexible and dynamic anchor placement. </t>
        

    </section>
<!--
    <section anchor="c-plane" title="Control Plane Considerations">
    
        <section anchor="existing-cplane" title="Existing Control Plane">
    
            <t>A mobile control-plane entity may allocate SIDs to the node
            of corresponding user-plane function. In this case, the
            control-plane entity must signal allocated SIDs to other side
            of entity. </t>
        
            <t>If the control-plane entity needs an existing mobile
            control-plane protocol to signal, GTP-C or PMIP for example, it must require
            not impact the control-plane protocols. In this case, a tunnel endpoint IPv6
            address field in the control-plane message can be used to signal a SID. </t>
            
            <t>The basic mode described in <xref target="traditional_mode"/> should be adopted.
            In the basic mode, SID indicates unique session so that tunnel identifier 
            is not required to SRv6 user-plane. But the mobile control-plane may
            assume that one user-plane entity has one IPv6 address and it allocates 
            one tunnel identifier per session. In this case, SRv6 node of user-plane can
            form SID with the IPv6 address and the tunnel identifier. </t>
            
            <t>When an IPv6 prefix "A::/64" is allocated to an user-plane, and 
            the control-plane allocates one 32-bits tunnel identifier of "0x12345678" for a
            mobile session, the user-plane node forms a 128-bits SID "A::1234:5678".</t>
            
            <t>In this way, there is no impact to the control-plane.</t>
            

        </section>
        
        <section anchor="aggr_cplane" title="Aggregate Mode">
        
            <t>To support aggregate mode as described in <xref
            target="enhanced_mode"/> for a control-plane protocol, allocated SIDs
            for service policies can also be signaled as a tunnel endpoint IPv6 address.
            In this case, the SRv6 policy associated to the SID should be configured
            in the user-plane node through other means.</t>
            
            <t>Aggregate mode user-plane can take advantage of SRv6 that
            enables seamless mobile user-plane deployment with service chaining,
            VPNs, traffic-engineering by computing a path to fulfill the policy.</t>
            
            <t>If a mobile control-plane is aware of those policies and is 
            capable to advertise them, the mobile control-plane can integrate
            SRv6 advanced features.</t>
        
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="cups" title="User-Plane Separated Control Plane">

            <t>In an user-plane separated control-plane system, a mobile
            user-plane entity may allocate SIDs to an user-plane function
            instead of the control-plane. In this case, the user-plane
            entity should inform allocated SIDs back to the control-plane
            entity.</t>

            <t>If the control- and user-plane entities need to employ
            existing user-plane control protocols in between, such as PFCP
            <xref target="TS.29244"/>
            for example, it may be required not to impact that protocol. In
            this case, the control-plane entity only is allowed to signal
            SID in a tunnel endpoint IPv6 address field. </t>

        </section>
        
        <section anchor="centralize-sdn" title="Centralized Controller">

            <t>When a centralized controller that interfaces to mobile
            control-planes is capable to allocate SIDs to the controlling SRv6
            nodes, the mobile control-planes just needs to indicate 
            nodes and their user-plane functions to the controller. In
            this case, the controller must allocate appropriate SIDs for the
            user-plane functions to the SRv6 nodes. The controller
            must configure allocated SIDs to the nodes. </t>
        
            <t>To indicate nodes and their user-plane functions from mobile
            control-plane to user-plane, the centralized controller could take
            advantage of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dmm-fpc-cpdp"/>. It provides
            interface to the control-plane to manage the user-plane of mobile
            networks. To build centralized controller for mobile user-plane is
            out of scope of this document.</t>

        </section>
        
        <section anchor="iwf-cplane" title="Stateless Interworking">
        
            <t>A mobile control-plane is not required to configure stateless interworking
            function in interworking node. This benefits operators to gradually migrate
            from legacy to advanced mobile user-plane with no impact to the legacy system.</t>
        
            <t>SID allocating entity of SRv6 user-plane nodes needs to be aware of
            IW-IPv6-Prefix to form interworking SID. Legacy user-plane network allocate
            IPv4 address space routed to SRv6 user-plane network. The mobile control-plane
            of legacy user-plane also need to allocate tunnel endpoint IPv4 addresses from
            that address space for mobile sessions which is usual operation for it and no
            difference from legacy system.</t>
        
        </section>   
    </section>
-->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    
        <t>TBD</t>
    
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    
        <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledge" title="Acknowledgements">
    
        <t>TBD
<!--        
        The authors would like to thank Daisuke Yokota,  Bart Peirens,
        Ryokichi Onishi and Kentaro Ebisawa for their useful comments of
        this work. -->
        </t>
    
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
        &rfc2119;
        &I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing;
        &I-D.filsfils-spring-srv6-network-programming;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
        &I-D.ietf-dmm-fpc-cpdp;
        &rfc5213;
        <reference anchor="TS.29281">
            <front>
                <title>General Packet Radio System (GPRS) Tunnelling
                Protocol User Plane (GTPv1-U)</title>
                <author surname="3GPP" fullname="3GPP">
                </author>
                <date month="December" year="2017" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS 29.281" value="15.1.0" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TS.29244">
            <front>
                <title>Interface between the Control Plane
                and the User Plane Nodes</title>
                <author surname="3GPP" fullname="3GPP">
                </author>
                <date month="December" year="2017" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS 29.244" value="15.0.0" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TS.23501">
            <front>
                <title>System Architecture for the 5G System</title>
                <author surname="3GPP" fullname="3GPP">
                </author>
                <date month="November" year="2017" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS 23.501" value="15.0.0" />
        </reference>
    </references>


  </back>
</rfc>